Finding aid for News and Information Services (University of Michigan) records, 1900-[ongoing]
Bentley Historical Library
News and Information Services (University of Michigan) records
1900-2008
1943-2008
Bentley Historical Library
University of Michigan. News and Information Services.
87265 BImu C475 2
164 linear feet
1 oversize volume
Serves as media relations office and disseminates information about university programs, research, events, and faculty activities. Includes correspondence, press releases, newspaper clippings, and other papers concerning the activities and work of the University, notable campus events, research, and teaching.
The News and Information Services (Donor no. 285 ) of the University of Michigan first began transferring its records to the Michigan Historical Collections in 1939. Periodic accessions have been received since then.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
News and Information Services (NIS) is the media relations office of the University of Michigan. NIS disseminates (to internal and external audiences) information about university programs, research, and activities of faculty and staff, primarily through the news media. NIS also responds to media requests for information about the university. Staff is comprised of information officers and editors covering specific university units, a photography unit, and a radio and television unit. This office also publishes The University Record, a weekly newspaper for faculty and staff, and Michigan Today, a quarterly tabloid newspaper sent to U-M alumni (complete sets of these publications are held by the Bentley Library). Some units on campus handle media relations through offices largely independent of NIS. These units include sports information, the Medical Center, the College of Engineering, Law School, and Business School.
News and Information Services has undergone several name and organizational changes, but can trace its roots to 1897, when the Regents requested a plan for to disseminate University news to the State. This original department of information services was primarily responsible for publishing newsletters and frequently struggled to finance its operations. By 1930, the need for a news agency had grown, and following the installation of President Alexander G. Ruthven, the university created a News Dissemination Service (often called the University of Michigan News Service). Led by Wilfred B. Shaw, the Service had two primary functions. First, it was responsible for preparing weekly releases for nearly 800 newspapers throughout the state and beyond. This reporting included news about the Regents, research conducted by professors, affairs of the student body, and all other campus news with the exclusion of athletics. The second function was to send news about individual students to their home town papers. (Michigan Alumnus May 27, 1959).
Originally part of the Bureau of Alumni Relations, in 1942 the University News Service, now led by Donald K. Anderson, became an independent department. In 1946, Arthur L. Brandon was appointed as the Director of Information Services and took over responsibility for the public information services on behalf of the University, services which included the University News Service, news photography, and promotional publications. In 1948, services expanded with the acquisition of the WUOM radio station and continued to adapt to new media with the addition of television.
With the administrative changes resulting from the installment of President Harlan H. Hatcher, Brandon's title was changed to Director of University Relations and the University News Service became part of the Office of University Relations. Other changes followed, with Regents meetings being opened to the press in 1954 and University News Service taking on photographic coverage at athletic events in 1956. In 1957, Brandon resigned from his position and was replaced by Lyle M. Nelson. As Director of University Relations, Nelson combined radio and television under the director of broadcasting. Nelson retired in 1961 and was replaced by Michael Radock. One year later, administrative reorganization created an Information Service.
The Information Service consisted of three divisions, including News Service, News Photography, and Community Relations. Further reorganization in 1963 and 1964 moved the publications and editorial services under the umbrella of Information Services and saw the promotion of Cleland B. Wyllie, who had been with the News Service since the 1940s, to Director of Media Relations.
While the Office of University Relations underwent several changes and reorganizations in the following years, Information Services remained under its jurisdiction until 1998, when the office was divided into three vice presidential posts. One of these new posts was the Vice President for Media Relations, which was responsible for the University's News Service. In 2000, the Media Relations became the Office of the Vice President for Communications, which is where the current News Service resides in the University organization. News Service has continued to expand its media types and now includes podcasts, social media, and other online resources in addition to its print, radio, and television services.
Current information about News and Information Services and on-line versions of the University Record and Michigan Today (with searchable back issues of the Record from September 1992, and Michigan Today from December 1993) is available on the Web at the following URL: http://ns.umich.edu/new/.
Summary Contents List
Correspondence Files
Correspondence, 1900-1943 [box 1]
Director's correspondence, 1946-1951 [box 2]
Editor's correspondence, 1946-1951 [boxes 2-3]
Director of University Relations correspondence, 1950-1959 [boxes 3-11]
Press Releases
Press release file, 1945-1956 (arranged topically) [boxes 12-28]
Press release file, 1957-1958 (arranged topically) [boxes 28-35]
Press release file, 1959-1960 (fragmentary) [box 35]
Press release file, 1963-1990 (arranged chronologically) [boxes 50-53, 77-78, 120]
Miscellaneous
Project Submich, 1967 [box 35]
Cleland Wylie topical files [box 42]
Scrapbook, 1976, primarily concerning President Ford's visit to U-M campus (Outsize volume, BImu/C475)
Topical files (including clippings, press releases and background materials)
1971 [boxes 36-38]
1972 [boxes 39-41]
1973 [boxes 42-45]
1974 [boxes 46-49]
1975 [boxes 54-56]
1976 [boxes 57-59]
1977 [boxes 60-63]
1978 [boxes 64-67]
1979 [boxes 68-72]
1980 [boxes 73-76]
1981 [boxes 80-84]
1982 [boxes 84-88]
1983 [boxes 89-92]
1984-1985 [boxes 93-100]
1986 [boxes 101-106]
1987 [boxes 106-113]
1988 [boxes 113-119]
1989 [boxes 121-127]
1990 [boxes 127-131]
1991 [boxes 131-135]
1992 [boxes 135-138]
1993 [boxes 138-140]
1994 [boxes 140-142]
1995 [boxes 142-144]
1996 [boxes 144-147]
1997 [boxes 147-149]
1998-2002 [boxes 161-166]
Audio-Visual Material
Audio-tapes of news briefs and 'actualities' [box 35]
"Report to the Community" 1975-1980
"Tomorrow '98": In the Upper Galilee (videotape)
Faculty and Staff Files [boxes 151-160] were removed to the News and Information Service Faculty and Staff Files collection during reprocessing. See separate finding aid for UM. News and Information Services Faculty and Staff files, 1944-2005
The News and Information holdings document how the university is portrayed in the media and the efforts of the university to promote itself. Although there is some correspondence from 1900-1903 and the 1930s, the bulk of the records date from 1946 to the present. The value of the files is as a source of ready information (on a yearly basis) about the activities and research accomplishments of university faculty and staff, departments, colleges and schools, libraries, centers, and other units. The records also chronicle notable events and visits by famous scholars and celebrities through yearly topical files, press releases, and correspondence. News and Information Service holdings also contain extensive photographic material (prints, negatives, slides, and transparencies) generated by the photography unit in addition to non-photographic records. The substantial photographic holdings are described in a separate finding aid.
The non-photographic News and Information Services records include some correspondence of the unit's administrators, although the bulk consists of news clippings, published materials, press releases, and other background information collected by NIS and arranged topically by year. The records are organized into eight series: CORRESPONDENCE, PRESS RELEASES, MISCELLANEOUS, TOPICAL FILES, GERALD R. FORD, UNIVERSITY PRESIDENTS, and ARCHIVED WEBSITES.
Academic freedom -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; Poliomyelitis vaccine.; Clippings.; University of Michigan -- History.; University of Michigan. News and Information Services.; University of Michigan. News Service.; University of Michigan. Information Services.; University of Michigan. Poliomyelitis Vaccine Evaluation Center.; University of Michigan -- Faculty.; University of Michigan -- Research.; Nickerson, Mark.; Davis, Chandler.; Markert, Clement L. (Clement Lawrence), 1917-1999.
- Correspondence Files, 1900-1959
  The CORRESPONDENCE series (11 linear feet, 1900-1903, 1929-1959) is arranged in four subseries: Correspondence, 1900-1903, 1929-1943; Director's Correspondence, 1946-1951; Editor's Correspondence, 1946-1951; and Director of University Relations Correspondence, 1950-1959. Most correspondence is with newspapers, magazine publishers, other universities, and radio and television broadcasting firms and associations.
  The earliest correspondence, 1900-1903, includes letters written to Ralph Ellsworth relating to inquiries asking other universities about their information dissemination activities. Correspondence from 1929 to 1943 is chronologically arranged material sent and received by Roger Morrisey and Wilfred B. Shaw and reflects some of the alumni information activities once handled by the office as well as contact with press agencies and newspapers throughout Michigan and the nation
  Director's Correspondence, 1946-1951, and Editor's Correspondence, 1946-1951, are similar in content. These two alphabetically arranged subseries comprise the correspondence of Arthur L. Brandon and Cleland B. Wyllie along with some other staff members. Wyllie served as editor but also handled other responsibilities within the office.
  The most substantial subseries is the Director of University Relations Correspondence, 1950-1959, arranged alphabetically by topic. It is primarily the correspondence of Arthur L. Brandon. Topics include academic freedom and anti-communism activities (filed under "subversive activities"), the 250th anniversary of Detroit's founding, Harlan Hatcher's inauguration as president, controversy surrounding the renaming of Michigan State University, atomic research sponsored by the Phoenix Project, the 1955 Salk Polio vaccine testing and announcement, and radio and television broadcasting. General information on university activities and programs appears throughout the files, which also include scattered press releases, articles, and clippings in addition to the correspondence. Newspapers and magazines doing stories on the university, such as Life, are well represented within this subseries.
  - General (Box 1)
    - Undated, 1900-November 1943 (Box 1)
  - Director's Correspondence (Box 2)
    - [A-Z], 1946-1951 (Box 2)
  - Editor's Correspondence
    - A-I, 1946-1951 (Box 2)
    - J-Z, 1946-1951 (Box 3)
  - Director of University Relations Correspondence, 1950-1959
    - "A" General (Box 3)
    - Admissions (Box 3)
    - Advertising Permits (Box 3)
    - Alice Crocker Lloyd Laboratory (Box 3)
    - Alumnae Correspondence (Box 3)
    - Alumni Correspondence (Box 3)
    - Alumni Clubs (Box 4)
    - Alumni Club of Detroit (Box 4)
    - Alumni Relations--Howard Peckham (Box 4)
    - American College Public Relations Association, 7 folders (Box 4)
    - American Council on Education (Box 4)
    - Arab Conference, 1952-1953 (Box 4)
    - Asian-American Seminar, 1956 (Box 4)
    - Association of American Colleges (Box 4)
    - Association of Governing Boards of State Universities and Allied Institutions (Box 4)
    - Athletics (Box 4)
    - Athletics, Board in Control of Intercollegiate
      - Meeting Minutes, 1958 (Box 4)
      - Meeting Minutes, 1957 (Box 4)
      - Meeting Minutes, 1952-1957 (Box 5)
    - "B" General (Box 5)
    - Band (Box 5)
    - Big Business Magazine clippings and others (Box 5)
    - Big Nine Group (Box 5)
    - Big Ten Group, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Big Ten-Television and Radio (Box 5)
    - Bnai B'rith Broadcasting Committee (Box 5)
    - Budget -- Departmental, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Budget -- Information and News Service (Box 5)
    - Budget -- Television Broadcasting (Box 5)
    - Budget -- University Relations (Box 5)
    - Building Programs (Box 5)
    - Bureau of School Services (Box 5)
    - Business Administration, School of (Box 5)
    - "C" General (Box 6)
    - CBS--TV (Box 6)
    - Charles University (Prague) (Box 6)
    - Children's Hospital (Box 6)
    - College-Industry Conference, 1953-1954 (Box 6)
    - Committee on College Relations (Box 6)
    - Conference Service Bureau (Box 6)
    - Counterattack (see also Subversive Activities) (Box 6)
    - "D" General (Box 6)
    - Deans (Box 6)
    - Decade of Achievement, 1957 (Box 6)
    - Degrees-Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - Detroit's 250th Anniversary, 1951 (Box 6)
    - Development Council
      - Alumni Fund (Box 6)
      - Alumni Public Relations Committee (Box 6)
      - Board of Directors (Box 6)
      - Executive Committee (Box 6)
      - General Correspondence (Box 6)
      - Organization Charter (Box 6)
      - Regents (Box 6)
    - "E" General (Box 6)
    - Education, School of (Box 6)
    - Educational Interpretation, Committee on (Box 6)
    - Engineering Centennia1, 1953 (Box 7)
    - Engineering, College of (Box 7)
    - Engineering Research Institute (Box 7)
    - Enrollment Statistics (Box 7)
    - Extension Service (Box 7)
    - "F" General (Box 7)
    - Football Ticket Requests, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Ford Foundation (Box 7)
    - Freedom of Information, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Fund for Adult Education (Box 7)
    - "G" General (Box 7)
    - Gifts, Grants or Contracts (Box 7)
    - "H" General (Box 7)
    - Hatcher
      - Inauguration (Box 7)
      - Letters written by Arthur Brandon (Box 7)
      - Memos from Arthur Brandon (Box 7)
      - Reports to the people of the state of Michigan Hatcher-Special Luncheons (Box 7)
      - Speeches, statements, releases written by Arthur Brandon (Box 7)
    - "I" General (Box 7)
    - Institute for Social Research, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - "J" General (Box 8)
    - "K" General (Box 8)
    - Kellogg Continuing Center (Box 8)
    - "L" General (Box 8)
    - Labor (Box 8)
    - Literature, Science and the Arts, College of (Box 8)
    - "M" General (Box 8)
    - McPhaul Dinner, March 6, 1952 (Box 8)
    - Michigan Council of State College Presidents (Box 8)
    - Michigan Health Council (Box 8)
    - Michigan State University (Box 8)
    - Michigan State University-Name change, 1954-1955; 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Michigan Week (Box 8)
    - Mission of Michigan Meeting, 1955 (Box 8)
    - Mission of Michigan Meeting, 1956 (Box 8)
    - Mission of Michigan Meeting, 1957 (Box 8)
    - "N" General (Box 8)
    - National Association of State Universities (Box 9)
    - Netherlands-Visit of Queen Juliana, April 17, 1952 (Box 9)
    - North Campus (Box 9)
    - "O" General (Box 9)
    - Official Publications, Committee on (Box 9)
    - "P" General (Box 9)
    - Personnel Office (Box 9)
    - Philippines, University of the (Box 9)
    - Phoenix Project
      - Continuation Program (Box 9)
      - General Correspondence (Box 9)
      - Memorial Building Dedication (Box 9)
      - News Bulletins (Box 9)
      - Newspaper clippings (Box 9)
      - Publicity (Box 9)
      - Speakers and Speeches (Box 9)
    - Policy Committee (Box 9)
    - Polio Vaccine, 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Principal-Freshman Conference (Box 9)
    - Public Relations (Box 9)
    - Public Relations, Committee on, 1950 (Box 10)
    - Public Relations Society of America (Box 10)
    - "Q" General (Box 10)
    - "R" General (Box 10)
    - Radio
      - Athletics (Box 10)
      - Budget (Box 10)
      - Executive Committee
        - 1947 (Box 10)
        - 1948 (Box 10)
        - 1949 (Box 10)
        - 1950-1951 (Box 10)
        - 1952-1953 (Box 10)
        - 1954-1957 (Box 10)
      - General Correspondence (Box 10)
      - Personnel (Box 10)
      - Programs (Box 10)
      - Promotion (Box 10)
      - "They Fought Alone" Series (Box 10)
      - Upper Peninsula (Box 10)
    - Regents, Board of (Box 10)
    - Religious Education (Box 10)
    - RKO-Pathe, Inc. (Box 10)
    - Rose Bowl (Box 11)
    - Ruthven, Alexander (Box 11)
    - "S" General (Box 11)
    - Scholarships (Box 11)
    - Science Proposal for Institute of Science and Technology (Box 11)
    - Soo Locks Centennial Committee, 1954 (Box 11)
    - Soviet Plastics Delegation Visit, 1958 (Box 11)
    - Speakers (Box 11)
    - Speech Department (Box 11)
    - Speeches and Articles (Box 11)
    - Student Publications, Board in Control of, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Subversive Activities, Communism, and Academic Freedom Surveys (Box 11)
    - "T" General (Box 11)
    - Town Hall of the Air (Box 11)
    - TV
      - Accounts (Box 11)
      - Athletics (Box 11)
      - Beaumont Project (Mackinac Island) (Box 11)
      - Butterfield-Gowthorpe (Box 11)
      - Channel 12 (Box 11)
      - Citizens Committee for Educational TV (Box 11)
      - Cooperation with other stations (Box 11)
      - Detroit Educational TV Foundation (Box 11)
      - Development, Committee on, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Educational TV and Radio Center (Box 11)
      - Educational TV Channels and Joint Committee (Box 11)
- Topical files
  The largest series, TOPICAL FILES (106 linear feet, 1971-2003), consists of yearly alphabetically arranged topical files ("Academic Affairs" to "WUOM"). Folders typically contain a mixture of newspaper clippings of articles prepared by the news service and articles written by others about the university. Many of the articles are from external clipping services, while others were collected by staff members from local publications such as the Ann Arbor News and Michigan Daily. Some press releases and press packets are included in the files long with occasional brochures and fliers. The arrangement maintained by the news office roughly mirrors the organization of the university. A wealth of material exists within these files. For tracking a unit or program area for a specific year, these files are particularly useful. However, locating information on specific events requires some advanced knowledge to make full use of these files. For example, articles about the apprehension of Unabomber suspect Theodore Kaczynski, a former graduate student in mathematics, are files under "Mathematics, Department of" in the 1996 Topical Files. Similarly, the 1995 Topical file for "Public Health, School of" includes material on Jonas Salk and the 40th anniversary of the Polio vaccine announcement.
  - 1971
    - Academic Affairs, Office of the Vice President, 1968-1975 (Box 36)
    - Admissions, Office of (Undergraduate), 1971 (Box 36)
    - Adult Education (Box 36)
    - Aerospace Engineering Department (Box 36)
    - Affirmative Action (Box 36)
    - Afro-American and African Studies, 1971 (Box 36)
    - Alumni Association, 1971 (Box 36)
    - Anatomy (Medical School), 1971 (Box 36)
    - Anesthesiology (Medical School), 1971 (Box 36)
    - Anthropology (LSA), 1971 (Box 36)
    - Appropriation, 1971 (Box 36)
    - Architecture and Design, College of, 1971 (Box 36)
    - Argonne Universities Association (Box 36)
    - Art, Department of (Box 36)
    - Asian Studies, 1971 (Box 36)
    - Astronomy (LSA), 1971 (Box 36)
    - Automotive Engineering Lab, 1971 (Box 36)
    - Band (University), 1971 (Box 36)
    - Biological Sciences, 2 folders (Box 36)
    - Biological Station, 1971 (Box 36)
    - Botanical Gardens, 1971 (Box 36)
    - Budget (Box 36)
    - Buildings, 1971 (Box 36)
    - Business Administration, School of, 1971 (Box 36)
    - Business Research, Bureau of, 1971 (Box 36)
    - Chemical and Metallurgical Engineering (Box 36)
    - Chemistry (LSA), 1971 (Box 36)
    - Chinese Studies, Center for, 1971 (Box 36)
    - Civil Engineering, 1971 (Box 36)
    - Classical Studies (LSA), 1971 (Box 36)
    - Clements Library, 1971 (Box 36)
    - Commencements, 1971 (Box 36)
    - Commission on Women, 1971 (Box 36)
    - Committee on Institutional Cooperation, 1971 (Box 36)
    - Computer Center, 1971 (Box 36)
    - Continuing Education of Women, Center for, 197 (Box 36)
    - Continuing Engineering Education, 1971 (Box 36)
    - Continuing Legal Education, Institute of, 1971 (Box 36)
    - Cooley (Thomas) Lectures, 1971 (Box 36)
    - Coordination of Ancient and Modern Studies, Center for the, 1971 (Box 36)
    - Dearborn Campus (Box 36)
    - Dental Research Institute, 1971 (Box 36)
    - Dentistry, School of, 1971 (Box 36)
    - Detroit Area Study (Box 36)
    - Development Office, 1971 (Box 36)
    - Economic Development, Center for Research on, 1971 (Box 36)
    - Economics (LSA), 1971 (Box 36)
    - Education, School of, 1971 (Box 36)
    - Engineering, College of, 1971 (Box 37)
    - English Language Institute, 1971 (Box 37)
    - Enrollment, 1971 (Box 37)
    - Environmental and Industrial Health, 1971 (Box 37)
    - Environmental and Industrial Health, Institute of, 1971 (Box 37)
    - Environmental Quality, Institute of (Box 37)
    - Exhibit Museum, 1971 (Box 37)
    - Extension Service, 1971 (Box 37)
    - Faculty, 1971 (Box 37)
    - Far Eastern Languages and Literature (LSA), 1971 (Box 37)
    - Fees, 1971 (Box 37)
    - Financia1, 1971 (Box 37)
    - Financial Aid, Student Office of, 1971 (Box 37)
    - Flint College, 1971 (Box 37)
    - Fresh Air Camp, 1971 (Box 37)
    - Geography (LSA), 1971 (Box 37)
    - Geology and Mineralogy (LSA), 1971 (Box 37)
    - Gerontology, Institute of, 1971 (Box 37)
    - Graduate Studies, Horace H. Rackham School of, 1971 (Box 37)
    - Grants and Contracts (private foundation), 1971 (Box 37)
    - Grants and Contracts (state, federal), 1971 (Box 37)
    - Great Lakes Research Division (IST), 1971 (Box 37)
    - Health Service, 1971 (Box 37)
    - Higher Education, Center for the Study of, 1971 (Box 37)
    - Highway Safety Research Institute (IST), 1971 (Box 37)
    - Honors (faculty), 1971 (Box 37)
    - Honors (students), 1971 (Box 37)
    - Honors Council (LSA), 1971 (Box 37)
    - Hopwood Awards, 1971 (Box 37)
    - Hospital Administration, Bureau of and Program In, 1971 (Box 37)
    - Human Adjustment, Institute of (Box 37)
    - Human Growth and Development, Center for, 1971 (Box 37)
    - Human Performance Center, 1971 (Box 37)
    - Human Relations Coordinator, 1971 (Box 37)
    - Industrial Relations, Bureau of, 1971 (Box 37)
    - Information Services, 1971 (Box 37)
    - Institute of Social Research (Box 37)
    - Intercollegiate Athletics, 1971 (Box 37)
    - Interlochen, 1971 (Box 37)
    - International Center, 1971 (Box 37)
    - International Commerce, Institute for, 1971 (Box 37)
    - Internal Medicine (Med), 1971 (Box 37)
    - Journalism (LSA), 1971 (Box 37)
    - Kellogg, W.K. Foundation (Box 37)
    - Kelsey Museum (Box 37)
    - Kresge Hearing Research Institute, 1971 (Box 37)
    - Labor and Industrial Relations (Box 37)
    - Law School (Box 37)
    - Learning and Teaching, Center for Research on, 1971 (Box 37)
    - Legislature (Michigan), 1971 (Box 37)
    - Libraries (Box 37)
    - Library Science, School of, 1971 (Box 37)